<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God save the King: or Pious and loyal joy, the subjects duty, for their soveraign's safety. Opened in a sermon at Aldermanbury, upon the 30 of May, being the day after his Majesties most happy, joyfull and triumphant entrance into London. By Anthony Walker, minister of the Gospell at Fyfield in Essex.</title>
            <author>Walker, Anthony, d. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1030_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203980</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858748</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96682)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1030[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God save the King: or Pious and loyal joy, the subjects duty, for their soveraign's safety. Opened in a sermon at Aldermanbury, upon the 30 of May, being the day after his Majesties most happy, joyfull and triumphant entrance into London. By Anthony Walker, minister of the Gospell at Fyfield in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Walker, Anthony, d. 1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M.S. for Thomas Parkhurst, at the three Crowns against the lower conduit in Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168890:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOD SAVE THE KING: OR PIOUS AND LOYAL JOY, The ſubjects Duty, for their SOVERAIGN'S SAFETY.</p>
            <p>Opened in a Sermon at <hi>Aldermanbury,</hi> upon the 30 of <hi>May,</hi> being the day after his Majeſties moſt happy, joyfull and Triumphant Entrance into <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Anthony Walker,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpell at <hi>Fyfield</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the three Crowns againſt the lower Conduit in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168890:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168890:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE <hi>CHARLES,</hi> Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> Baron of <hi>Leez.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the Analogy be true betwixt natural and morall ſtreams, that as in waters, ſo in affections, the flowings will equalize the elevation and ſite of the ſpring-head, from whence they are derived, &amp; joy in fruition of deſired good will be proportionate to that deſire which did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed fruition: I am well aſſured the ſubject of theſe leaves will find a full agreement in your Noble breaſt, that I ſhall need make no Apology for venturing to adorn them with your Honourable Name. For as I had the honour to be a witneſſe of your moſt ardent longings to ſee theſe productions of deep and aſtoniſhing Providence, which we then wanted faith to believe; and which have ſince filled all honest Loyal boſomes with ſuch Extaſies of delight and thankfulneſſe, ſo am
<pb facs="tcp:168890:3"/> I more then confident, no heart reſounds and ecchoes to this Joyful, Pious, Loyal ſhout, <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> more cheerfully, more loudly, more faithfully then yours; theſe papers therefore muſt be your Lord-ſhips, by a double due, both as I am yours, and incluſively all that's mine, as all the iſſue of the ſervant was his Lords, <hi>Exod. 21.4.</hi> and as they are the tranſcript and coppy of your very heart. Let me only beg the favor to give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in an inverted order of the preaching, and publiſhing of them. What is ſtoryed of the dumb ſon of <hi>Craeſus,</hi> that ſeeing a hand ſtretcht out to ſlay his father, he brakt the very bars of nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his lips till then were cloſed up, and all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, cryed out, <hi>Kill not the King,</hi> is in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure exemplified in this publication; the like paths hath over-ruled me, and what fear did in him f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the death of a living King, that joy in me for the life of a dead King, dead in his enemies ſtrong deſires, proud hopes, and cruel reſolutions, dead in his peoples fears, diſpondencies, and diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all means of reſtauration, till Gods time came, <hi>and the mighty were taken away without hands, Job 34.20.</hi> whom we have received as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did <hi>Iſaac,</hi> from the dead in a figure, who hath been with S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> in deaths often, and eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:168890:3"/> the ſnares of treachery and violence more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly then he did at <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> My admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and rejoycings I ſay at theſe great ſalvations of God, have broke my hitherto obſtinate ſilence, as to this manner of publique ſpeaking, for the preaching of it, I muſt confeſſe I ſcarce ever prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched any Sermon with leſs preparation then I firſt preached this, and after once preaching it, had ſhap't and moulden my thoughts into this method, I found it hard to alter it, So that tis, as to the main, the ſame I ſuddenly delivered at <hi>Burnt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> Lecture, <hi>May</hi> the <hi>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> upon the joyful Newes of his <hi>Majeſtyes</hi> Proclaiming, that I have preacht it ſeverall times ſince, both in City and Country in eminent auditoryes, is ſo well known I cannot hide it, eſpecially at <hi>Alderman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> when the City did yet ring and eccho with thoſe repeated acclamations, and I hope it needs no farther excuſe then the obvious intimation, that it teaches a duty almoſt obſolete and out of faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, very ſeaſonable and neceſſary to be learnt, and that, though plainly, yet I hope pertinently, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and piouſly. But this I muſt ſubmit to the cenſure of others, which I ſhall ſcantly, and with leſs ſolicitouſneſs doe, if it may obtain your Honours favourable acceptance, and be owned as
<pb facs="tcp:168890:4"/> a Religious teſtification of conſciencious Loyalty to my <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and a pledge of his ſelfe Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to your Lordſhips ſoul-intereſts and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My moſt Noble and very good Lord</salute>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt devoted Orator, and moſt humble Servant, ANTHONY WALKER.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>June <hi>15. 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:168890:4"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe ſeaſonableneſs of the Text, the occaſion of the words, they are to be handled intirely, opened in the fourfold notion of them; 1. As a joyful <hi>Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;</hi> 2. As a Pious <hi>Apprecation;</hi> 3. As a due atteſtation of their Allegiance; 4. As a ſeaſonable recordation of humane weakneſs, and need of Gods ſalvation. <hi>pag.</hi> 1, 2.</item>
               <item>From the firſt notion of them ariſeth the firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>That 'tis lawful and of good report to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt our rejoycings at the ſetting up of rightful Kings.</hi> Six Spring-Heads of their joy, they rejoyce 1. for the bleſſing of Civil Magiſtracy, 2. For the beſt forme of it, Monarchical. 3. For a King of Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al extraction. 4. Not only a King but the King, one of the right Line, and the true Heire. 5. One of the true Religion. 6. All this brought to paſs ſo ſuddenly with little blood ſhed, and the great quiet and ſatisfaction of the people, in all which our cauſe equalizeth or exceedeth theirs. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. to <hi>p.</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>From the ſecond notion of the words ariſeth this ſecond Obſer: <hi>That as 'tis lawful to rejoyce at the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of Kings, ſo 'tis neceſſary to pray for them when ſet up.</hi> Here what we pray. 1. For long life for the King, or that God would ſave him from thoſe natural evils which are evil to him as a man, inforced with 4 reaſons. <hi>p.</hi> 13, 14. 2. a proſperous life, or that God would ſave him from civil, publick evils evils to him as a King. <hi>p.</hi> 15. wherein that proſperity conſiſts, and what thoſe evils are, this inforced from the inſeperable connection of the happineſs or miſery of Prince &amp; people <hi>p.</hi> 16, 17, 18. 3. for a gracious holy life, or that God would ſave him from thoſe ſpiritual evils, which are evil to him as a Chriſtian, this inforced by 6 weighty and cogent motives, <hi>p.</hi> 19, 20, 21. 4. for
<pb facs="tcp:168890:5"/> an everlaſting life, or that God would ſave him from eternal evils, which are evil to him as a man, a King, a Chriſtian, this inforced 1. from the truth of our love to him, no love being true or conſiderable which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not the eternal welfare of the parry beloved; 2. from Chriſtian generoſity in our compoſition, moved by the ſad ſuppoſal, of the aggravated miſery of a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying King. <hi>p.</hi> 22. Secondly, why we muſt thus pray for Kings, inforced by 4 virtues; <hi>p.</hi> 23, 24.</item>
               <item>From the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> notion of them, ariſeth the 3. Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>As 'tis lawful to rejoyce, neceſſary to pray, ſo 'tis our bounden duty, to atteſt Allegiance freely and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly,</hi> how to do this, inforced by reaſons, 1. in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the King, 2. to the publick, 3. to each private Subject. <hi>p.</hi> 25, 26. From theſe put together <hi>they rejoyce, they teſtifie Allegiance, yet they pray piouſly,</hi> reſults the 4. Obſerv:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>We need not borrow of prophaneſs to pay our debt of thankfulneſs to God, or Allegiance to our Soveraign.</hi> Rejoycing threefold; Civil, Religious, Prophane; the two firſt allowed and required, the laſt condemned, &amp; with juſt indignation deteſted. <hi>p.</hi> 27, 28. the abuſe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Majeſtyes ſacred name in forcing men to drink, by pretending it a character of disloyalty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to drink his health, a free conjecture at the firſt original of drinking healths upon the knees, <hi>p.</hi> 29.</item>
               <item>From the 4 aſpect of the words ariſeth the 5 Obſer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That 'tis very ſeaſonable in the midſt of triumphant rejoycings, to mind both King and People of humane weakneſs and need of Divine ſalvation,</hi> inforced with reſpect both to King and People. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion by way of recapitulation commending the King to Gods ſalvation in all the forenamed reſpects.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168890:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Pious and Loyall Joy,</hi> The Subjects duty for their Soveraigns ſafety.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Chronicles 23.</hi> verſ. <hi>11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>—God ſave the King.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Text is ſo very ſeaſonable, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wiſh the Sermon to be more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. I have choſen it to raiſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie our preſent juſt rejoycings, and to help you do that knowingly, which you do ſo heartily; <hi>That what you pray with your ſpirits, you may pray with your underſtandings alſo,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> directs; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of the words lyes open and obvious in the cloſe of the 22. ch. and the beginning of this 23. take but this brief account of it, becauſe they are ſo full, that they command all our time to veiw and make improvement of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Atthaliah</hi> that wicked woman, as ſhe's called, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.7. Having boldly uſurped the Royal dignity of the Crown of <hi>Judah,</hi> after ſhe had barbarouſly murdered all the ſeed royal of the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> except <hi>Joaſh</hi> only, the youngeſt ſon of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> who by that pious loyalty, and compaſſionate duty of <hi>Jehoehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beath,</hi> wife to <hi>Jehojodah</hi> and daughter to King <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> had been ſtoln from amongſt his brethren which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168890:6"/> were ſlain, and was preſerved by her prudent care, hid in a chamber of the Temple. He being now grown into ſome capacity of ſwaying the Scepter, and being preſented to the people, and taking upon him the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Government. <hi>Jehojedah</hi> the chief Prieſt by his wiſe and zealous interpoſing with the Captains and Commanders of the Army, brought them to a ſence of their duty, and withal of their happineſſe; and by the forwardneſſe of the honeſt <hi>Levites,</hi> and chief Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the King is brought forth; and ſet up, and ſolemnly inveſted in his Princely power; and while the other juſt Ceremonies are performed by ſelect hands, the whole multitude do with freeneſſe and alacrity diſcharge that part of the ſervice they were fitted for, by approving of, and by rejoycing at what paſſed, and with a joyful, pious, loyal acclamation, cry <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble you with any diviſion of the words, no! let the King and Gods ſalvation never be divided, the method in which I ſhall handle them, is only to conſider their ſeveral aſpects, as they look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people, God and the King, as expreſſions of their gladneſſe in themſelves, their devotion towards God, and loyalty unto the King, and what ariſeth thence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And thus they are <hi>Laeta acclamatio Gaudii,</hi> An exulting acclamation of their joy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Pia apprecatio boni,</hi> A Pious apprecation of good in the Kings behalfe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Debita atteſtatio Fidelitatis,</hi> a due and bounden atteſtation of their Allegiance.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Tempeſtiva recordatio humanae fragilitatis,</hi> A ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable reminding both of the King and themſelves
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168890:6"/> of humane frailty and impotence, and their need of divine ſalvation and protection both for King and People. And in this order I ſhall ſpeak to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with the firſt, as they are <hi>laeta acclamatio gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dii,</hi> an exulting and triumphant reſounding out of their rejoycings in God, and bleſſing him, for giving them a King to bleſs him for.</p>
            <p>And thus the firſt obſervation from their practice will be this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it's</hi> Licitum et honeſtum, <hi>A thing lawful,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſerv:</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>honeſt, and of good report, to teſtifie our gladneſs and rejoycing at the ſetting up of rightfull Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prayer and Praiſe are of ſuch affinity that 'tis not leſs proper, then much frequent to expreſs one in the form of the other, and what is prayer for the matter, is praiſe for the manner of it, frequently in Scripture. This very phraſe hath been cuſtomary to ſignifie their rejoycings and thankſgivings by on like occaſions. When <hi>Saul</hi> was inveſted in his Kingdome, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon the ſight of him, cryed out, <hi>God ſave the King;</hi> And it was not only a cuſtome, but a ſolemn inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and appointment, given in charge by <hi>David</hi> at the Inauguration of his ſon <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.33. <hi>Cauſe Solomon my ſon to ride upon my own Mule, and bring him down to Gihon. And let Zadock the Prieſt, and Nathan the Prophet anoint him King over Iſrael, and ſay God ſave King Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the ſtreams of their joy, which flowing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into one channel, make ſuch a ſpring-tide of gladneſſe, ariſe from theſe ſix <hi>Heads;</hi> and our caſe and theirs do run ſo paralel, that theirs will illuſtrate ours, without any further Application.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168890:7"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Head.</hi>
               </note>The firſt Head is;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſetting up of civil Magiſtracy this is juſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis no ſmall bleſſing to humane ſociety, to obtain this Ordinance of God, without which, <hi>Homo homini lupus,</hi> Each man would be a Wolf or Tiger to his neighbour, and therefore Kings are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The foundations of their people, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Shields of the earth, the Shepherds of the flock, the Scept and Hedge of Religion, Peace and Property, the Fathers of their Country, and Nurſes of the Church. If notwithſtanding the ſevere diſcipline which God hath appointed to keep the world in awe and order, yet mens luſts force them; Upon the very point and edge of the Magiſtrates ſword, what bounds or meaſure would they know, if that reſtraint were taken off. Certainly he ſaid not amiſs, who ſaid, <hi>'Tis better living where nothing is lawfull, then where all things are lawful,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Sine imperio nec domus ulla, nec civitas, nec gens, noc homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> univerſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſtare nec verum natura omnis, nec ipſe mundas durare poteſt. <hi>Cicero</hi> de legib.</p>
                  <p>Cum dicitur non fuiſſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem in Iſrael, innuntur mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non eſſe turbidam fuiſſe tunc religionem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trempublicam. Hinc nata eſt idolatria bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum alienorum direptio: quia rex non erat, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, qui male iſta cohiberet. Agnoſcamus hinc, quanti ſit faciendus Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus: qui ſi bonus fuerit, et Rempublicam et cultu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei continet cuſtos: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Et ut ut malus ſit ad tuendam co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem hominem ſocietatem, Reipub. multis modis prodeſt. <hi>Pet. Mart.</hi> in Locum.</p>
               </note> and the hazard is leſs, in all reſpects of being reſtrained from, or puniſht for the doing ſomething well, then to be left at liberty to do, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer what our own or others luſts may force upon us. Twas the top &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the bad condition of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Laiſh. Judg.</hi> 18.7. <hi>That there was no Magiſtrate in the Land to put any man to ſhame in any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the great inſtance is, <hi>Judges</hi> 17.6.18.1.19.1. in all which places 'tis ſaid, <hi>In thoſe dayes there was no King in Iſrael, every man did what was right in his own eys.</hi> Then it was, that that prodigious lewdnes was acted in <hi>Gibeah</hi> upon the <hi>Levites</hi> Concubine, and the whole Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> made acceſſary, <hi>poſt factum,</hi> by abetting and patronizing ſo flagitious a wickedneſſe, then was that <hi>minor</hi> idolatry ſet up in <hi>Micahs</hi> houſe, and that increaſt into a more ſpreading
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168890:7"/> and accumulated miſchief in the Apoſtacy and vile defection of an whole Tribe; which thereby became the accurſed Tribe, of which none are mentioned to be ſealed, in the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> where twelve thouſand are ſealed of every Tribe beſides, and <hi>Dan</hi> which ſhould have judged his people, for want of a King to judge them, ran upon eternal Judgment.</p>
            <p>And indeed civil Magiſtracy is ſo great a mercy that it coſt no leſs then the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt to purchaſe it:<note n="a" place="margin">Propter pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſtorum non ſolum ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus &amp; aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis futurae vitae bonis, ſed etiam et corporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus hujus vita commodis, genus humanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excidit ſed Deus ex miranda et nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſatis p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>edi cauda beniguita te propter filij interceſſionem, non illa ſolum ſed etiam haec reſtituit ac reparavit, ac media illis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervandis ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navit inter quae eminotpoliticus Magiſtratus. <hi>Gerard.</hi> de mag. <hi>Polit.</hi>
               </note> for man by his apoſtacy from God and rebellion againſt him, forfeited the benefit and bleſſing of order, and deſerved to be let looſe to Ataxy and Anarchy and all moſt ſad confuſions, but Jeſus Chriſt interpoſed and by his mediation prevailed with his Father in behalfe of humane ſociety, to avert the vengeance and procure this bleſſing, <hi rend="sup">b</hi> 
               <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.15. <hi>By me Kings reigne, and Princes decree juſtice, by me Princes rule even all the Judges of the earth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> that is, Jeſus Chriſt, that is, not only by me are the perſons appointed, but by me is the inſtitution pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, and continued. 'Tis a diſputed caſe whether Magiſtrates be immediately under God the Creator, or God-man the Redeemer, but the arguments are many and cogent on this latter ſide, and the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityes many, grave and learned, but I muſt wave all at preſent. And this ſhould as it ſtrongly ingageth, earneſtly excite and quicken Magiſtrates, to be moſt careful of Chriſts concernments, and to rule for him, by whom they rule. And thus for the firſt Head, and wel-ſpring of their joy, the enjoyment of the bleſſing of civil Magiſtracy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſecond ſource of their rejoycing was that they had not only civil Magiſtrates, but the beſt form of civil Magiſtracy, Monarchy or Kingly Government,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:168890:8"/> which that tis ſo, So: the Arguments are obvious and copious,<note n="b" place="margin">Ipſo dei filius</note> if time would admit the bringing them to view. As the Antiquity, <hi>Monarchicus ſtatus eſt omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am antiquiſimus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">impiorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutionem et conſervationem ſibi tribuit quia per Chriſtum mediatorem non ſolum ſpiritulia et aeterna, ſed etiam crpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia et tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia beneficia generi hum. ſuntcredita intro qua eminet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutio Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus.</note> Aguſt. The firſt the world was ever acquainted with. Moſt agreeable to nature, natures light ſuggeſting, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and all Nations of the earth when guided by its light did know no other. <hi>Aſſirians, Medes, Perſians,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis the lively Image of Paternal Government, as the Father hath authority and power over his children. The oeconomick Government of every Family, in which one Lord or Maſter, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bias</hi> ſmartly anſwered him, who mov'd for a Common-wealth: Sir, <hi>Make experiment of it in your own family, before you commend it to the publick,</hi> and nature gives emblems of it in the Bees, the Cranes, &amp;c. Farther</p>
            <p>Moſt comprehenſive of the advantages of other Governments, and leaſt ſubject to their inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or dangers, and proved the beſt by great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the continuance and flouriſhing of it beyond any other, and that to which others who moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and decryed it, were often glad to be behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in ſtreights and difficulties. As by the <hi>Romans</hi> ſetting up Dictators ſo frequently appeares. But theres one ſo glorious no foggs of Ignorance can Eclipſe it's evidence, the one Sun to rule the day, and in a different ſence, both to obſcure, and enlighten all the common people of the ſkies, and another ſo ſuperlative that no Impiety dares to deny or queſtion it, one God to rule the higher houſe of Angels, and the lower houſe of men, and all things with and under them.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168890:8"/>
            <p>But one Text of Scripture is ſufficient,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.6.</note> where to wave what flowes from <hi>Moſes</hi> being King in <hi>Jeſurun,</hi> and Gods promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> that Kings ſhould come of him. We know Gods own deciſion and ſuffrage, advancing a Kingdome above all other puny forms of Optimacy or Democracy. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.13. — <hi>Thou didſt proſper into a Kingdome.</hi> The whole ſcope of the place is to enumerate the mercies and favours heaped by the Lord upon this ſinfull people of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and to upbraid their non-improvement, yea their vile and baſe returne made to ſo good a God for all his mercies Now if it were not a bleſſing and advantage to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be raiſed and proſpered out of a meaner and a baſer condition into a Kingdome, it were no aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their fault, that t'was againſt him who had done ſuch things for them, and ſo exalted them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Third ſpring of their ſtreame of joy was,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Head.</note> 
               <hi>that they had the kingly government mannaged by a kingly hand, the Son of ancient Kings to ſit upon the Throne.</hi> Tis a reproach to a people to be ruled by vile and meane men, when God ſets up the baſeſt of men, and lets ſervants have dominion, he doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe his own ſupremacy, but debaſeth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth a nation whom he deals ſo with. But 'tis the great advantage both in poynt of honour and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when honourable and princely perſons rule, and the Majeſty of the governour, is not only an ornament but Munament, unto the Government it ſelfe; that the Nation is neither deſpicable for his obſcurity, nor ſubject to mutinies by the multitude of Competitors to the Throne, upon which many will eſteeme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and be eſteemed by others, as fit to fit, as ſuch an one, therefore <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Bleſſed art thou O Land when thy King is the Son of Nobles:</hi> by high entraction
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168890:9"/> and ſuteable education ſhaped to the honourable and difficult worke of government.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Fourth Head of joy was, that they had not only A King, but The King, the juſt and righteous</hi> Heir, one of the blood Royall of the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> upon whom the Lord himſelf had intail'd the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the houſe of <hi>Judah.</hi> And ſurely this is great and juſt matter of rejoycing, to ſee that pinching hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſnare broken, which hath alwayes been ſo ſore a rack to tender conſciences, I meane the yielding of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to undue, and to uſurped powers. The honeſt men in Judah were in great ſtraights, and none can expreſſe their caſe, but ſuch as taſt and feele it, when they were relieved in it. 'Tis an heavy and affrighting Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2. <hi>They that reſiſt, receive to themſelves damnation;</hi> and we had need to feare the very ſhadow of it paſſing over us. 'Tis a very great refreſhment to be ſet at freedome from that ſnare and danger, and to have nothing elſe to inquire, but the lawfulneſſe, and goodneſſe of things commanded, that either they may be obeyed with alacrity and freeneſs, or we may ſuffer with cheerfullneſſe, and peace of conſcience, which will be an Antidote and Cordiall in ſuch tryalls, and I aſſuredly believe, that many good men find it as irkſome and preſſing a trouble to be commanded lawfull things by unlawfull powers, as unlawfull things by powers which are lawfull.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The Fift Head of this joyfull ſtreame was, that the Lord had given them a King of the true Religion, to be a nurſing father to his Church;</hi> the true Religion was under great oppreſſion; <hi>Atthaliah</hi> though a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, was a maſculine Idolatreſſe, ſuperſtition was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rampant, <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> Calves were not only growne Bulls, and ſtrong enough to puſh with the horne of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168890:9"/> perſecution all that would not fall down and worſhip them, but were multiplied into an Heard, ſo that all the conſecrated ground in <hi>Iſrael</hi> was too ſcant a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture for them, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.7. and truth had but a lean and neceſſitated tolleration. And it muſt needs be matter of triumphant refreſhment to recover freedom for Gods Ordinances and Worſhip after ſo black and dark ſuſpenſion and ſuppreſſion of them.</p>
            <p>The ſixt Head which filld this ſtream, was <hi>the manner of it, the ſudden ſurprize of mercy, an unexpected deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance beyond their faith and hope, when moſt conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſadly that all the royal ſeed were dead, and no ſtrong rod left to be a Scepter to rule,</hi> as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 19.14. and all accompliſht with ſo much peace and ſafety, ſo little blood, and all the people of the land rejoyced, and the City was quiet, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. <hi>ult.</hi> And doubtleſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved our rejoycings run paralel with theirs in all the ſprings and ſtreams, and if in any thing they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, it is by being over-meaſure; God hath bleſſed us with a Kingly Magiſtrate, a King, the King, not only the ſon of ancient Kings, but the rightfull heir and undoubted Lord of the Imperial Crown and dignity of this <hi>Brittiſh</hi> world. A King of the true Religion, moſt graciouſly preſerved ſo, notwithſtanding all the temptations ſpread before him by thoſe of contrary perſwaſion and profeſſion, with all imaginable advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages on the perſwaders parts, and all the unkind and ſcandalizing diſobligements from them of the ſame Faith and way of worſhip. Bleſſed be the Lord for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring to a Proteſtant people, a Proteſtant King, after ſo many eminent hazards both to the Proteſtant and to the King. The God of Heaven who hath kept him in the ſtorm of affliction from being broken, keep him in the Sun-ſhine of Proſperity from being warpt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168890:10"/> in any kind, I ſpeak it not as doubting, but imploring that eſtabliſhing grace, which may confirm him and enlarge his heart in the pureſt, and moſt zealous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it, more and more, that no damp may be upon the zealous rejoycings of thoſe to whom Gods glory, his honour is moſt truly dear; And to ſatisfie not your curioſity ſo much, as your ſerious rejoycings; I ſhall acquaint you with ſome paſſages which proceeded from his Princely lips, at the preſentment of the Bible to him by the Reverend <hi>London-Miniſters</hi> in his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the City. <q>I thank you for your prayers, and I deſire the continuance of them, and I aſſure you I ſhall make it my firſt care to ſet up Gods worſhip and ſervice, this is the book muſt guide us all, and I will make it the rule of my life and my Reigne.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly we have very ſolid cauſe to rejoyce that Religion is freed from ſo many dangers as did beſet it, over drop it, and ſuck at its ſap and vigor, and we humbly hope the dangers are not changed only, but removed wholly. 'Tis a mercy the very Text is not treaſon, that there is no <hi>Index expurgatorious</hi> upon our Bibles, to expunge ſuch verſes, that the whole Chapter is not <hi>Appocrypha,</hi> and that our whole Bibles are once more Scripture; And all this ſo wonderfully brought to paſs, with ſo unbloody triumphs, with ſuch unexpected ſuddenneſs, with ſo inlarged a ſatisfaction to the body of the Nation, and with ſuch ſignal diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of the Lords right hand in the doing of it, that we muſt cry out and ſay, <hi>'Tis the Lords own doing and it is marvelous in our eyes, this is the day which the Lord hath made, we will rejoyce and be glad in it.</hi> And this may ſuffice for the words in their firſt acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as they are <hi>Laeta acclamatio gaudii,</hi> The trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168890:10"/> and exulting acclamation of their joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I proceed to the ſecond as they are.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Pia apprecatio boni,</hi> a Pious and devout appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of good to be conferred and beſtowed upon him, in the Original tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> Let the King live, the words are ſhort and comprehenſive, and a common form of benediction, not unlike that other frequent and cuſtomary amongſt the <hi>Hebrews, pax tibi,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Life is the baſis, the foundation and lower ſtory upon which the ſuperſtructure of all other bleſſings are erected, the centre in which all other lives do meet; when we pray for life, we compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pray for all the benefits bleſſings and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which do accompany, and may attend it, and make it life indeed. And the matter will be little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, whether we keep to the ſtrictneſs of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, or take the liberty of our Tranſlation, which is a kind of paraphraſe upon the words. If the firſt then they are a direct apprecation of thoſe good things wherein life with the comforts of it do conſiſt. If in the latter a deprecation of thoſe evils contrary to it thus, <hi>Let the King live,</hi> that is, let him live a long life, 2. a proſperous life; 3. a gracious life; 4. an eternal life, or <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> that is, God ſave him from what is naturally evil to him as a man; 2. from what is civilly evil to him as a King; 3. from what is ſpiritualy evil to him as a Chriſtian; 4. from what is eternally evil to him in all reſpects, as a man, a King, a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>So the obſervation here is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That as it is lawful and of good report to rejoyce in the ſetting up of Kings, ſo 'tis</hi> honeſtum et neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, <hi>honeſt and a neceſſary duty to pray for them when ſet up to be Gods remembrancers, to preſerve
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168890:11"/> and ſecure them, to bleſſe them,</hi> as <hi>Solomons</hi> people did him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.66. that is, <hi>commend him hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to God to be bleſſed of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt explaine and then confirme this obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And I will begin with the firſt branch of it. <hi>Let the King live a long life,</hi> or God ſave the King from what is naturally evill to him as a man. You may have the meaning of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.4. <hi>He asked life of thee, and thou gaveſt it him, length of dayes for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> A life of long continuance, an Emblem and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a life which laſts for ever, or a life in his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſtretched, and eked out in a Kingly Progeny. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 61.6. <hi>Thou wilt prolong the Kings life, and his years as many generations.</hi> We here pray that the Lord would preſerve and prolong the naturall life of the King, and that he, who (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.10.) giveth ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto Kings, and preſerved <hi>David</hi> from the hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſword, would do ſo for our King, preſerve him from what may either take away his life, or imbitter it to him. And we are much concerned thus to pray that his life may be long and healthfull, lively, vigorous to diſcharge his office of governing his people to their beſt advantage. For</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Tis a token of Gods anger and diſpleaſure when the lives of Kings are ſhortned, &amp; thereby their number multiplied, Prov.</hi> 28.2. <hi>For the tranſgreſſion of a Land many are the Princes thereof;</hi> And great is the evill which befalls that Land, where the Kings dye young, before their poſterity be growne men of knowledg &amp; Authority: For when, (as he threatens, <hi>Iſa</hi> 3.4.) An angry God gives to a provoking people, <hi>children to be their Princes, and babes to rule over them.</hi> Verſ. 5. <hi>Then the people ſhall be oppreſſed every one by another, and every one by his neighbour.</hi> If therefore you would
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168890:11"/> be free from this reproach of being frownd on by a righteous God, and bearing the conſequents that iſſue thence, pray firſt that the King may live long.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Pray for a long life for the King, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the hazards and commotions which attend the change of Governours;</hi> What is the curſe of women, is the doome of Nations, to bring forth with danger, paine and ſorrow; we commonly ſee in the change of Princes, new deſigns, new Laws, new Officers, new Friends, new Enemies, new Habits, and a new form of living: for moſt commonly all Princes take a delight to alter all things, that they may be ſpoken of: the which doth oftentimes cauſe great inconveniences not only to the ſubjects in particular, but alſo to the whole body of the State. <hi>Bodin. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>ch.</hi> 4. Rarely doth the Throne Travell of a new King, but tis in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be rent in pieces: Turbulent ſpirits watch the advantage of an <hi>Inter-regnum,</hi> as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> did at the death of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and deſigne ſuch opportunities to ripen miſchief: And it is obvious that for the moſt part, the longeſt reigns have been the happieſt times, as <hi>David</hi>'s, <hi>Solomon's, Auguſtus, Queen Elizabeth,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore if you love the eaſe and ſafety of the people pray that ſuch hazards may be rare and few, by the long continuance of them who ſit upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Pray for the long life of the King, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of time may give him more knowledge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in the Art of Kingſhip.</hi> Certainly as ruling is one of the moſt high and noble imployments, ſo it is one of the moſt difficult Arts, and needs not only ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and excellent tools and inſtruments, as Laws and Counſellers, and Officers of State, and the like, but very much wiſdome to mannage, guide and uſe them all, which cauſed <hi>Solomon,</hi> (wiſe even then, or elſe he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168890:12"/> had not askt ſo wiſely) to beg of God (1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.9.) an underſtanding heart to judge his people, and to diſcern betwixt good and evill, and ſeeing infuſed ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits are acquired, as acquired ones are, though the Lord do graciouſly infuſe wiſdome and an heart fitted for government, as he gave <hi>Saul</hi> another heart when he deſign'd him King. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.9. yet time and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience do greatly advantage a Prince, and add to his wiſdome and underſtanding, and by ruling he beſt learns to rule. Three things much help a King to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern well, Firſt, Science or knowledge of the Rules of pollicy or government; Secondly, Obſervation of the errors or advantages of other Princes, in well, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applying thoſe Rules; Thirdly and Chiefly, Practice and experience, and this is the daughter and product of time; Practiſe is the great accompliſher of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, this makes the valiant and ſucceſſefull Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, this makes the bold and skilfull marriner, this makes the learned and the uſeful Phyſitian, this makes the convincing and ſavoury Miniſter, and this makes the truly wiſe, and excellent and glorious Prince. And it is continuance of time muſt helpe in this, 'tis that which gives him advantage to know his peoples temper at home, and their true intereſt abroad; what amities to contract, what offers to refuſe or chuſe, what injuries to revenge, or more ſafely and cheaply not to reſent and take notice of. From this lofty Pinnacle it is he hath the faireſt view and proſpect of the Counſells and deſignes of neighbouring Princes, which may make impreſſion on himſelf and people, and may ſee how to divert them, obviate or improve them, and therefore the loſſe of a prudent and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd King, oft puts ſuch a ſtand unto publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of the whole people, 'tis a damage ſcarce
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168890:12"/> reparable in an age. Therefore if you love but the honour and renowne of your people pray that the King may live long, that experience may ripen him for Government, and we long injoy the benefit and exerciſe of that experience.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Pray for long life for the King, becauſe long life is in it ſelf a bleſſing, a promiſed bleſſing which God hath often held forth in the Scripture as a very deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing,</hi> and is evidently ſo, not only as it is the bottom and foundation of all our good things here, for when life is gone, all is gone, but in reſpect of eternity our everlaſting condition depends upon this; Life is the day in which alone we can work for Heaven. <hi>The night cometh wherein no man can worke, (Joh.</hi> 9.4.) Life the longer it is, the more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage it giveth to know more of God, to do more for God, and to be fitted for fuller fruitions and injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of him to all eternity; Beg of God therefore to give the King this bleſſing, and the bleſſing of it, the beſt improvement of it to all the advantages and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits thereof.</p>
            <p>I come to the ſecond, <hi>Let the King live a proſperous and happy life, as a King, or God ſave the King from thoſe politick or civil evils, which are evil to him as a King, Proſperetur Rex,</hi> So the <hi>Targum</hi> renders it; this followes in order in the 21 <hi>Pſalme, v.</hi> 4. <hi>Thou gaveſt him length of dayes;</hi> then <hi>v:</hi> 5. <hi>His glory is great in thy ſalvation, Honour and Majeſty haſt thou laid upon him, for thou haſt made him moſt bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c. And that you may be the more excited thus to pray for him; conſider your own intereſt ingages you hereto, for the good and proſperity of King and People are involved and wrapt up in one another; theſe are thoſe twins, which muſt live or die together, it cannot
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168890:13"/> be well with head or members ſeverally, or diſtinct from each other, but they flouriſh or wither both, or neither; there cannot be a glorious King over a diſpirited and deſpicable, diſcontented people, neither can there be a renowned and a flouriſhing people under a mean, &amp; an inglorious Head. Now when you pray that your King may live a proſperous life as a King, you pray for a confluence of thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which may render King and people jointly and mutually happy in, and with each other.</p>
            <p>Now the happineſs of Kings as ſuch conſiſts; 1. In the multitude of his people; <hi>Prov:</hi> 14.28. <hi>In the multitude of people, is the Kings honour, but in the want of people is the deſtruction of the Prince;</hi> 2. In the peaceable ſubjection of his people, one of the moſt comely ſights in <hi>Solomons</hi> opinion is, <hi>a King againſt whom there is no riſing up; Prov.</hi> 30.31.3. In the proſperity, wealth, plenty, honour of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. 4. In the preſence of God with his people, that true Religion be loved and practiſed in the midſt of them, that God own them for his people, this was the honour of <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.8. <hi>To be King of a people whom God had choſen for his own, a great people to which the Lord was nigh.</hi> Then the happineſſe of a people in their King conſiſts in this; Firſt, That he be a wiſe prudent Prince, knowing how to go in and out before them and to judge them; This was <hi>Solomons</hi> petition, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.9. and this was his people happineſſe and glory to be ruled by ſuch an one. Secondly, That he be a juſt and righteous, and a merciful Prince, executing judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and doing juſtice, and relieving the oppreſſed, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3. <hi>He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the fear of God, and he ſhall be as the light of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168890:13"/> the morning when the ſun riſeth, even a morning without clouds, as the tender graſs ſpringing out of the earth, by clear ſhining after raine;</hi> 3. That he be a man of courage, valiant and publick ſpirited, that dare look danger in the face, and expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to hazards for his peoples ſafety when great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity requires it. Laſtly, That he be a lover of good men, <hi>one in whoſe dayes the righteous may flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Pſ.</hi> 72.7. See the character of an excellent King in the beginning of that <hi>Pſalm,</hi> where you find <hi>David</hi> begging of God to make <hi>Solomon</hi> ſuch, in a word, pray that the King may live a wiſe, a juſt, a valiant, and religious King over a numerous, a Loyal, a loving, a wealthy and religious people, and let him be ſaved by the Lord from what ever may hinder King or People from being ſuch. <hi>God ſave him</hi> from true enemies, and from falſe friends; from real adverſaries, and from pretended lovers. <hi>God ſave him</hi> from the hurtful ſword of forraine enemies, that either he may have none ſuch, or they may only be the matter of his victory and triumph. And <hi>God ſave him</hi> from domeſtick and inteſtine ſeditions, rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, inſurrections, that there be no ſtrife amongſt his Subjects, but to out-vy each other in pious Loyalty and juſt allegiance, that the hearts of his people may be his Throne, and the heads of his enemies may be his footſtool. <hi>God ſave him</hi> from falſe friends which ſhould either betray his good councils, or ſuggeſt evil councils to him, from ſuch as <hi>Joaſh</hi> met with in the 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.17. <hi>After the death of Jehojedah came the Princes of Judah and made obeiſance to the King, and the King hearkned to them, and they left the houſe of the Lord God of their Fathers, and ſerved groves and idolls:</hi> 'Tis not ſaid what the Princes ſpake, but it was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168890:14"/> curſed council which brought the wrath of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and ingaged the King in a great additionall ſin, even to command him to be ſtoned who was both the Lords meſſenger, and the ſon of them by whoſe loving and prudent fidelity his life had been preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and his Kingdome recovered. The Lord preſerve our King from all ſuch, <hi>and let the wicked be kept from about him, that his Throne may be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs;</hi> Prov. 25.5. and let that be his chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, <hi>Pro:</hi> 14. <hi>ult.</hi> which will be his perpetual honour, <hi>That his favour may be to a wiſe ſervant, and his wrath againſt them which cauſe ſhame.</hi> Take the ſum of what we are to pray for, in this ſecond branch, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently laid down by the Pen of holy <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 144.10, 11, &amp;c. where we have the King praying for himſelf and people, what we are to pray for our King and ſelves, having in the 10th verſe fitted himſelf to pray, and ſtrengthned his faith by putting upon God a ſutable Title, <hi>He that giveth ſalvation unto Kings, and by experience of former mercy, 'tis he that hath already delivered David his ſervant from the hurtful ſword,</hi> then he proceeds to pray to be <hi>rid and delivered from the hand of ſtrange children, whoſe mouth ſpeaketh vanity,</hi> that is, who vainly boaſt and threaten great things, <hi>and them whoſe right hand is falſhood,</hi> that is, who ſatisfie their faith, which they have ſworn by lifting up their hand, for that was the forme of ſwearing amongſt the <hi>Hebrews, Gen.</hi> 14.22. <hi>I have lifted up my hand unto the Lord, I have ſworn</hi> as we ſwear by laying the hand upon the Book. <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>That our ſons may be as plants grown up in their youth, that our daughters may be as corner ſtones, poliſhed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſimilitude of a Pallace: ver:</hi> 13. <hi>That our garners may be full, affording all manner of ſtore, that our ſheep
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168890:14"/> may bring forth thouſands and ten thouſands in our ſtreets, that our Oxen may be ſtrong to labor, that there be no breaking in, nor going out, that there be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining in our ſtreets, happy is the people that is in ſuch a caſe, yea happy is that people whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> This is to live like a King indeed, to live and rule a people compaſſed about with ſo ſweet a confluence of all good things, and all thoſe crowned with the preſence of God, and the flouriſhing condition of true religion, all which <hi>Hezekiah</hi> epitomizes, not inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catively, in two words <hi>truth and peace in his dayes,</hi> and this is what we do pray and ought to pray in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reſpect, Let the King live a proſperous and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py life, as a King. <hi>God ſave the King</hi> from thoſe civil, publick evils, which are evil to him as a King.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Let the King live</hi> a holy, gracious, Godly life, or <hi>God ſave the King</hi> from thoſe ſpiritual evils which are evil to him as a Chriſtian, and 'tis very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that we in this reſpect cry heartily <hi>God ſave the King.</hi> For</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is the moſt hopeful way to obtain the two foregoing petitions, for long life, and a glorious reign; for <hi>Prov:</hi> 3.16. of grace and wiſdom 'tis affirmed, <hi>that length of dayes is in her right hand, and in her left hand riches and honour,</hi> and Prov: 22.4. <hi>By the fear of the Lord are riches, honour and life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the King needs this as well, as much as other men, what is ſaid of the great Prophet, I mean <hi>Elijah,</hi> is true of the greateſt of Kings, <hi>He is a man ſubject to the like paſſions,</hi> Jam. 5.17. a peice of the corrupted maſs of fallen mankind, and a ſinner by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as really as other men, and needs renewing, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying, converting, quickning, purging, pardoning grace as well as other men.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168890:15"/>3. <hi>Becauſe the temptations of a King are more and ſtronger then of other men:</hi> Partly by reaſon of his very place &amp; ſtation, the height and fullneſs of it, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from thoſe many reſtraints which other men are awed by, &amp; eſpecialy from the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lice and ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Satan who knows how to do his work compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly, and therefore will be ready like the <hi>Syrians</hi> to fight <hi>neither with ſmall nor great,</hi> comparatively, <hi>but with the King of Iſrael,</hi> that by drawing a King to commit it, he may bring vice into faſhion and repute, and therefore pray earneſtly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>God ſave the King from ſpiritual evils, becauſe its of great concernment to the whole Nation, what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample the King ſets,</hi> for his practice is the grand coppy which moſt write after, and the lives of the people will be in great meaſure the counterpart of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Regis ad exemplum,</hi> &amp;c. So that all his good laws will hardly avail to counterpoyſe a bad example if the Lord ſhould leave him to himſelf to ſet one; and on the other ſide, 'tis a very great advantage to virtue and Godlineſſe, when 'tis commended by the Kings practiſe, as well as commended by his authority, if Religion and Piety be in credit and faſhion at the Court, 'twill be the mode and faſhion of City and Country, the wiſdome of God hath frequently made uſe of the converſion of Kings, to open a way for the Goſpel into their Dominions, yea and their peoples hearts too.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Becauſe the imployments of a King are great, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and weighty;</hi> and indeed the duties of the meaneſt of our callings will be too heavy for us, to be well borne, unleſs the Lord help us to ſuſtaine them, and how much more doth a King whoſe work is, as the nobleſt, ſo the hardeſt, need much Divine aſſiſtance,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168890:15"/> much grace, much help from Heaven to performe ſo great a truſt, to the glory of God, his owne comfort, and his peoples good.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Becauſe if God ſhould in anger leave the King to injoyne grievous and unlawful things,</hi> which I only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently ſuppoſe, to awaken your zealous prayers for him (but do not peeviſhly ſuggeſt, or ſullenly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad he will) <hi>how uncomfortable will your neglect of duty make your ſufferings, if you ſhould be called to ſuffer in ſuch caſe?</hi> for then will your conſcience fly in your face, and tell you, I may thank my owne neglect of duty for all this, if I had begged earneſtly for wiſdome, and the guidance of Gods holy Spirit for him, 'tis like ſuch things had never been injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and I now reap nothing but the juſt deſert of mine own folly and neglects, which certainly will be unpleaſant fruit, and one of the bittereſt drops in a ſorrowful unwelcome cup: In a word, ſeeing 'tis the grace and Spirit of God which ſanctifies all relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and fits and inables for the reſiſting the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons incident to them, and to perform the duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on us in them, let us pray heartily that God would beautifie the King abundantly, with thoſe plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful influences of his Spirit, which may render him at once the beſt of Kings and the beſt of men, and that he would ſave him from all the guilt, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and filth, and deceitfulneſſe of ſin, and what ever Spiritual evils, are evil to him as a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>God ſave the King from eternal evils, evil to him as man, as King, as Chriſtian.</hi> Let the King live an eternal life in Heaven, after a long and happy life on earth: <hi>Serus in Coelum redeat (Hor:)</hi> or in the words of a better Poet, the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 91. <hi>ult.</hi> Let God ſay of him, <hi>With long life will
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168890:16"/> I ſatisfie him, and ſhew him my ſalvation.</hi> And we ſhould with as much hearty earneſtneſs pray, and cry <hi>God ſave the King</hi> in this ſence, as in any, this is to be ſaved indeed: Alas! all other ſalvation is a poor low thing, without that ſalvation which is emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſo called, and ſhall never be changed or altered. Let me inforce this briefly:</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you love the King truly, you muſt pray thus for him, true love will conſtraine you, 'tis a falſe and a deſpicable and but a ſelfiſh love, which doth not ſtretch it ſelf out unto eternity: You love no man truly, whoſe ſoul you do not love, and certainly you love not that ſoule, concerning which you are indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and care not what becomes of it, care not though it periſh and be loſt and damn'd for ever: Can you ſay you love? and not be moved with the everlaſting prayers and ſorrows of thoſe whom you pretend to love? now be ſolicitous for their preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or removall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If there be any bowels of Chriſtianity, or but generous humanity in you, it will provoke you thus to pray for him eſpecially: For if a King miſcarry, O how terrible and ſad will his miſcarriage be: <hi>Potentes potenter,</hi> The mighty ſhall be mightily tormented, if they go to the place of torment, it may heat the coldeſt, and kindle the dampeſt devotions into flames of zeal to prevent ſo ſad a change, to conſider how horrid it will be to change the dignity, the ſplendor, the Authority and Majeſty of a Throne and Scepter into eternal bonds and darkneſſe, hunger, thirſt and cold, to extremity beyond imagination, to Vaſſalage under the baſeſt and vileſt piece of the whole Creation; it would be a dreadful alteration for the pooreſt of us, to change our meaneſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168890:16"/> for the flames of Hell, and unmixed wrath of the Almighty God; but what then for a King to fall from ſo high a ſtanding, <hi>graviori lapſu,</hi> and be inſulted over as the King of <hi>Babilon, Iſa.</hi> 14.9, 10. <hi>Hell from beneath is moved for thee, to meet thee at thy coming: it raiſeth up the dead for thee, even all the great ones of the earth, it hath raiſed up from their thrones, all the Kings of the nations. All they ſhall ſpeake and ſay unto thee, art thou alſo become weak as we? art thou become like unto us. Thy pompe is brought down —: How art thou fallen from Heaven?</hi> The thing it ſelf doth ſpeak ſo movingly that I ſhall add no more but as men amazed uſe to do, with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vehemence cry out, <hi>God ſave the King from thoſe eternall evills, that he may live an everlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reaſons why we muſt freely and cordially joyne in this pious Apprecation, that the King may live or be ſaved in all thoſe Reſpects, are</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The command of God,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.1, 2. <hi>I exhort therefore that firſt of all ſupplications, prayers, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men; For Kings, and all that are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty, for this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The fifth Commandement doth lay neceſſity upon us,</hi> and woe be to us if we be found wanting. He is our publick father, <hi>Pater patriae,</hi> our Countries fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it is one chief part of the Tribute of honour we owe to our ſuperiours, our humbleſt and our hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt prayers.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:168890:17"/>3. <hi>The example of the beſt and choiceſt of Gods ſervants alwayes making conſcience of this duty, even to and for bad Kings. Nero</hi> was King when St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy. Jehojedah</hi> and his ſons very good men and Prophets of God begat the cry, they cryed, <hi>God ſave the King:</hi> The Church and people of God, even when in <hi>Babilon</hi> prayed for the peace of it, and after their return did offer ſacrifice for the life of the King and of his ſons: And the mutes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented perſons at <hi>Saul</hi>'s inauguration are branded with a character of infamy, ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> who <hi>deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him and brought him no preſent.</hi> 1 Sam. 10.27.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>It is but an equitable retaliation;</hi> The King is loaded with the burden of cares for your ſafety and preſervation: a Throne is not ſo ſoft a ſeat as moſt men judge it, a thorne is its lively Anagram, you only ſee the ſhining outſide of a Crown, but feel not the harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er lining of its inſide, nor the preſſing weightineſſe with which it loads as well as adorns; if you did, you would envy leſſe, and pray and pitty more, and indeed if your burden bow him down, there is all reaſon you ſupport and ſtay him up, and by your prayers prop up his hands as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> did thoſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> that they may be ſteady in the management of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments.</p>
            <p>I come now to the third aſpect of the words, as they look upon the King directly, and fix the accent upon his name and Title: As they are <hi>debita attoſtatio fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitatis,</hi> a due and bounden atteſtation, and a vowed acknowledgement of their allegiance, and ſubjection to him as their King; <hi>jubilo ſuo ſe ſpontaneus regni ſui ſubditos profitenter.</hi> And here we have the third Obſervation.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:168890:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Tis very uſefull and convenient that upon the ſetting up of rightfull Kings, the ſubjects do freely and readily witneſſe and manifeſt their due and juſt allegiance and fidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As other Kingdomes are the ſhadowes of Chriſts Kingdome, ſo his is the great pattern and beſt exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of other Kingdomes; now of his it is ſaid, that <hi>his people are willing in the day of his power,</hi> and ſo ſhould other ſubjects be, a willing people, readily yielding their obedience in all lawfull things, as <hi>Davids</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.44. <hi>Aſſoon as they hear of me they ſhall obey me: the ſtrangers ſhall ſubmit themſelves unto me.</hi> We muſt be ſubject not for wrath, but for conſcience ſake, not grudgingly, nor of neceſſity, not becauſe we muſt, but becauſe we will, yea, becauſe it is Gods will we ſhould. And indeed that we thus do is of great concernment to Princes, to the Publike, and to each particular man.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>To the Prince,</hi> It contributes much to his eaſe and honour, and makes him a King indeed, when he knows he rules his people not againſt their wills, when he needs no guard againſt his people, but contrariwiſe <hi>Amor civium eſt pro ſatellitio,</hi> their love is his ſecurity and ſhield, and they bare him, as he bears his Crown, not as a load, but Ornament.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Tis much for the advantage of the publick, as to ſecurity and peace,</hi> and for prevention of commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and confuſions in the State. As many women looſe their chaſtity by forfeiting their modeſty, for did they give evidence, as grave and ſober matrons of a pious and reſolved purity, the moſt debaucht and profligate ruffian would not have impudence enough
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168890:18"/> to attempt them; but lightneſſe and looſe wearing of the vaile of modeſty, imboldens to that onſet which ends too often in a ſurrender: And thus it is with peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, their wavering, and unreſolved obedience, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages ſeditious and turbulent deſigners, upon pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick peace, and gives them but too too pregnant hopes of too too good ſucceſſe, in thoſe vile and dangerous attempts, from which they would with uttereſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair deſiſt, if people were, as they ought to be, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd, fixed and eſtabliſhed, in reſolved and juſt obedience to their Rightfull and undoubted Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>'Tis much for the peace and private good of each particular man,</hi> both as all ſingle Intereſts are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved and bound up in that of the publick peace and ſafety; and farther, becauſe ſubjects are rarely made the Butt of their Princes diſpleaſure, till they give ſome cauſe of jealouſie, and in a ſort neceſſitate ſome frowns for his perſonall or nationall ſecurity, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of ſome teeming miſchief.</p>
            <p>And for theſe and the like reaſons, it hath been, and ſtill is, the prudent and laudable cuſtome of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to teſtifie their willing ſubjection at the inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their Kings; the Nobles by ſome ſignall act of homage, as by explicite oath, by bending of the knee, by touching the Crowne or Scepter, by kiſſing of their Prince, to which the Pſalmiſt alludes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Kiſſe the Son, leſt he be angry, oſculo</hi> ſc. <hi>ſubjectionis,</hi> or ſome ſuch like action, and all the people to atteſt their concurrence with them, in ſuch demonſtrations of their duty, by hearty and reiterated acclamations like to this, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will now put theſe three together and give the reſult of them, they rejoyce, they atteſt their allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168890:18"/> and they do both theſe in a pious and pertinent religious forme of prayer, Whence their ariſeth this fourth Obſervation,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the beſt rejoycing is Religious rejoycing, made ſweet and ſavory with the name of God,</hi> or thus, <hi>We need not borrow of profaneſſe to pay our debt of thankfulneſſe to God, and allegiance to the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That's good melody, Chriſts, which is ſo in heaven which jarrs not, nor ſounds harſh in the holy ears of God, that harmony which makes no diſcord with pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but 'tis ſad mirth which grieves the holy Spirit, and very treaſonable allegiance which caſts off obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the King of Kings. There is a threefold rejoycing, Civill rejoycing, religious rejoycing, and prophane rejoycing: the firſt is lawfull, the ſecond is neceſſary, but the third is neither lawfull nor neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but very abominable and hatefull to a bleſſed God, and burdenſome and grievous to all ſober, and honeſt men. I may ſay of it, (<hi>Jam.</hi> 4.16.) <hi>All ſuch rejoycings are evill.</hi> And indeed the mingling ſo much prophaneſſe with ſome mens joy, hath put a damp upon the rejoycings of many ſober and godly men, and forced them to withdraw from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of your gladneſſe, not through unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to teſtifie their gladneſſe, for the Lords great and gracious goodneſſe to the King and Nation, which was as true, as hearty, and enlarged as any mens; but for fear of partaking with them in the ſinfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their rejoycings, and leſt they ſhould ſo ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the Lords kindneſſe, as to provoke and ſadden him, for relieving and gladding us. I beſeech there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168890:19"/> and adjure ſuch men not to ſeek occaſions, or take up a reproach againſt the moſt ſober and moſt loyall in the Land, as if they were leſſe glad, becauſe leſſe madd then ſome men, as if true joy were incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with ſobriety and ſeriouſneſſe, when the truth is, it is altogethet inconſiſtent with the want of them, for <hi>res eſt ſevera verum gaudium,</hi> Seneca. True joy is a very ſerious and rationall affection as any that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorns mans nature. And for your ſelves, O that I could prevaile with you, to pray for the King more, and to drink and ſwear (I will not call it for him, though too many doe, but) for your luſts, leſſe. Oh how uncomely is it, for the ſame mouth to cry, God ſave the King, and then to bid defiance to heaven, with dreadfull God damne themſelves, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Out of the ſame mouth proceedeth bleſſing and curſing: my Brethren theſe things ought not ſo to be.</hi> If you pray for him, make not ſuch a <hi>dam</hi> in the channell of your own prayers, as muſt ſtop the current of them, but ſo live as your prayers may be heard, and do him good; You know or ſhould know, if you regard iniquity God will not regard your prayers, God heareth not ſinners. Firſt, wilfull and flagitious ones; <hi>but if any man be a worſhipper of God, and do his will, him he heareth,</hi> Joh. 9.31. And indeed ſuch Practices are ſo far from being expreſſions of thankfulneſſe that they are incompetent and inconſiſtent, the Apoſtle oppoſes them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.4. — <hi>But rather giving of thanks.</hi> He that gave charge, that our communication ſhould be alwayes ſavoury, ſeaſoned with ſalt, that it might miniſter grace to the hearers, never gave an excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that rule, or a toleration that at times of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick rejoycing it might be rotten or prophane. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he who put thoſe two together, <hi>Fear God, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168890:19"/> honour the King,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. well knew that we might honour the King without caſting off the fear of God. I have met with a gloſs upon that paſſage of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 24.21. <hi>My ſon fear thou the Lord and the King, and medle not with thoſe who are given to change;</hi> that is, who do <hi>tranſmutare ordinem,</hi> ſet the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have ſpoken ſomewhat here concerning drinking healths, ſo much urged and practiſed by very many men, and lookt upon as if it were the onely character of a Loyal Subject, for my part I confeſſe I think they have made a very unhappy and a rude choice to expreſſe their honour to the King by; I judge his name too Auguſt, too Sacred and Reverend a thing, to be ſoakt and ſopt in every cup; yea, pardon the expreſſion, for vile practiſes neceſſitate to homely compariſons, to be made uſe of as a Farriers horn to force down that drink which neither the man, nor the beaſt (for ſo drunkenneſs leaves them, which it found men) would ſwallow, but for feare of being judged disloyal: but the moſt offenſive poſture of this blind zeale, is when it transforms men into more perfect pictures of the Worſhippers of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> defiles and proſtitutes a conſecrated geſture, and brings them on their knees, perhaps a caſual invention, began by ſome, who had drank themſelves off their leggs, and when they could ſtand no longer, would make a devout vertue of their unhappy neceſſity, to which they were forced as a more ſteady poſture. I confeſſe I want a name bad enough for this cuſtome, and O that I could fairely perſwade men out of it, as a moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and very ſcandalous practice. If it be good, as I allow it is, to rejoyce and to atteſt and manifeſt our
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168890:20"/> Allegiance, yet do both ſo, as may be of good report, let not then your good be evill ſpoken of, and think it not enough to ſay, 'tis none but a few ſuch or ſuch preciſe fellows are offended; Remember what the Apoſtles tenderneſs and caution was, <hi>Whether ye eat or drinke, or whatever ye do, do all to the glory of God; Give none offence to the Jew, nor to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, nor to the Church of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31, 32. They who are offended cannot be leſs conſiderable then ſome of thoſe of whom he here makes mention, and if the matter were leſs liable to exception, and it were, their only weakneſs to take offence who do ſo, yet it would become you to remove the occaſion, and not to reflect reproach upon our Loyal and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, yet Pious and Religious rejoycings. I ſhall conclude with one intimation, that the King will not take this ſo kindly as you vainly think he will, for amongſt many other gracious words which fell from his gracious lips, when he received the <hi>London</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which went to him at the <hi>Hague,</hi> he had theſe memorable and rare expreſſions;</p>
            <p>
               <q>That he would make it his buſineſs to bring virtue and ſobriety into faſhion and repute in <hi>England,</hi> and though there were a prophane drinking party which would be eſteemed his beſt or only friends, he would make the more haſte into <hi>England,</hi> to let ſuch men know that he was their worſt enemy, for they were the Devils party, and none of his, and which is the true honour of them, they were free and ſo continue, not drawn from him or ſuggeſted to him.</q> His Majeſties moſt excellent Proclamation againſt prophaneſſe and debauchery, publiſht ſince the preaching this, &amp; which hath ſo exceedingly refreſht, and afreſh indear'd him, to his loving, Loyal, ſober ſubjects: And thus for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168890:20"/> the 4. obſervation reſulting from the conjunction of the manner how they expreſſe their joy and atteſt their loyalty, in a gracious, ſavory, and uſeful prayer, that God would ſave him, whom they freely owne, and gladly acknowledge as their King.</p>
            <p>I come to the laſt aſpect of the words, as they are <hi>Tempeſtiva recordatio humanae fragilitatis,</hi> and look upon both King and People to mind them ſeaſonably of humane frailty and weakneſſe, and how much even Kings do need Gods Salvation and Defence, and here we have the fifth and laſt Obſervation:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis very ſeaſonable and neceſſary when King and People are in greateſt glory and ſtate, to mind them of their own weakneſſe, and their need of Divine Protection and Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God ſave the King:</hi> Though we love him, and would lay down our lives for him, yet we cannot ſave him, unleſs the Lord ſave him, <hi>In vain is ſalvation looked for from the hills, and from the multitude of mountains, truly in the Lord our God is the ſalvation of Iſrael,</hi> both of King and People, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108.6. <hi>That thy beloved may be delivered ſave with thy right hand: v:</hi> 12. <hi>Give us help from trouble, for vain is the help of man: Pſal.</hi> 33.16, 17. <hi>There is no King ſaved by the multitude of an hoſt: a mighty man is not delivered by much ſtrength. An horſe is a vain thing for ſafety, neither ſhall he deliver any by his great ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.1. <hi>Except the Lord build the houſe they labor in vain that build it, except the Lord keep the City the watch-man waketh but in vain.</hi> The Scripture moſt frequently and abundantly ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth this, and 'tis never more needfull and ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168890:21"/> to be meditated then at ſuch ſolemn times, when the ſtrength, and riches, and ſplendor of a Kingdome is diſplayed together: And firſt, 'tis very uſeful for the King then to remember the weakneſſe and inſufficiency of other helpers, then is the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion like to be ſtrongeſt to carnal confidence in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtrength, when it is ſet out with all its bravery and gliſtering gallantry; then is the heart in moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be ſtollen away and to forſake the Lord; Gods own caution doth evidently ſuppoſe this, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.11, 12. &amp; 8.10. <hi>When thou haſt eaten and art full, beware that thou forget not the Lord thy God: ver:</hi> 12. <hi>Leſt when thou haſt eaten and art full,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 14. <hi>Then thine heart be lifted up, and thou forget the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>And thou ſay in thine heart, my power and the might of my hand, hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me this wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was beholding the great <hi>Babylon</hi> which he had built by the might of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and for the houſe of his Kingdome, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Majeſty, then it was that his pride pul'd down that heavy doome, <hi>a voice fell down from Heaven, Dan.</hi> 4.30, 31. It was when <hi>Herod</hi> was arrayed with Royal apparel, and ſat upon his Throne, and was applauded with the ſhout and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of the people, that he provoked ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance by the hand of an Angel, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.22, 23. But to inſtance in better men 'twas a temptation too ſtrong for <hi>David,</hi> even he in his proſperity waxed over confident, and ſaid, <hi>that he ſhould never be removed, Pſal.</hi> 30.6. And too great for good <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> for when great honour was done to him, <hi>his heart was tickled and taken with it, his heart was glad,</hi> Iſaiah 39.2. that is, vainely and proudly:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:168890:21"/> ſo as to pull an heavy ſentence down from God, which was delivered by the Prophet in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſes. So that not only the <hi>proſperity of fools deſtroys them,</hi> (Prov. 1.32.) but the Honour and Glory of the beſt men will enſnare and endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger them, if they be not very heedful and mindful of their weakneſſe and inſufficiency in the midſt of all their greatneſſe, and therefore wiſe Princes have uſed to daſh the wine of their joy with ſome morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying water, to correct its intoxicating and inebria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting force. Hence was that ſolemn right in the inſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Eaſtern Emperours, a Lapidary preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting variety of ſtones, and beſpeaking him to this ſence, <hi>Chooſe Mighty Sir, under which of theſe ſtones your Highneſs pleaſes to inſhrine your bones.</hi> And <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> had a Deaths head ſerved to his Table at the greateſt feaſts, and <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> had a boy every morning to be his remembrancer, crying at his door, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſtill at the Popes inauguration, the Cerimony of the Tare, with a <hi>Sic tranſit gloria mundi,</hi> is in uſe. And <hi>Saladine</hi> the <hi>Sultane</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> had an old Shirt carryed on a Pike before him, with Proclamations made, this is all that <hi>Saladine</hi> Conqueror of <hi>Aſia</hi> ſhall carry out of the world with him; and to the ſame good purpoſe may this expreſſion, <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> ſerve, even to mind him that the love of his moſt Loyal people, and the ſtrength of his moſt valiant Souldiers, and the wiſdom of his moſt prudent Council, and the riches of his moſt wealthy Citizens, are not ſufficient to preſerve him, but he muſt doe it, <hi>who alone it is, that giveth ſalvation unto Kings,</hi> Pſal. 144.10. and he may be helped freely to give the Lord the glory both of paſt and future ſalvations, in the words of <hi>David,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:168890:22"/> Pſal. 44.6, 7. <hi>I will not truſt in my bow, neither ſhall my ſword ſave me: But thou haſt ſaved us from our enemies, and haſt put them to ſhame that hated us;</hi> or as his Majeſty graciouſly expreſſed himſelfe in his ſhort Speech to the Miniſters, in his paſſage through the City:</p>
            <q>The deliverance which God hath wrought for me I own as the work of his own right hand, beyond hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane contrivance, and deſire that all the glory of them may be aſcribed to him.</q>
            <p>And 'tis ſeaſonable and uſeful to the people alſo at ſuch time to be put in mind how much both King and people need of the help of God to ſave them, for then is the greateſt fear of idolizing earthly deities, when they ſhine not only with the rayes of their own Majeſty, but are made dazeling &amp; reſplendent by that brightneſſe which the flaming zeal, and blazing love and Loyalty of their faithful people doth reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; 'Tis a well tim'd meditation therefore for the people at ſuch a ſeaſon to conſider what they ſay, when they cry out, <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> if he with all this help about him, yet needs <hi>God to ſave him,</hi> how much more do we; if he cannot ſave himſelfe unleſſe God ſave him, then neither can he fave us, without his aid, as that King confeſſed; 2 <hi>King:</hi> 6.27. and the words are good, though he were otherwiſe, who ſpoke them, If the Lord do not help thee, whence ſhall I help thee, and it may aſſure us <hi>that its better to truſt in the Lord, then to put confidence in Princes, Pſ.</hi> 118.9. and may teach us, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 146.3. <hi>Not to put truſt in Princes, nor in the ſon of man in whom there is no help.</hi> To conclude therefore, let it be our care and practiſe, as to love him affectionately, and rejoyce in his proſperity and honour heartily, and teſtifie our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:168890:22"/> Allegiance freely and cheerfully, ſo to pray for him moſt humbly and earneſtly, as knowing that (as he hath been pleaſed to deſire prayers, ſo) he greatly needs them, for he cannot ſave himſelfe, he cannot ſave his people, nor can they ſave him, but muſt be beholding to the Lord to ſave them all; Therefore (Pſal. 21.) <hi>Let the King joy in thy ſtrength, O Lord, and in thy ſalvation let him greatly rejoyce: Give him his hearts deſire, and with-hold not the requeſt of his lips, prevent him with the bleſſing of thy goodneſſe, and ſet a Crown of pure Gold upon his head, give unto him long life, yea length of dayes for ever and ever: Let his glory be great in thy ſalvation, lay upon him Majeſty and Honour; yea ſatisfie him with long life here, and ſhew him thy ſalvation hereafter:</hi> God Allmighty ſave him from all natural evils, which are evil to him as a man, and <hi>God ſave him</hi> from all civil evils which are evill to him as a King, and <hi>God ſave him</hi> from Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al evils, which are evil to him as a Chriſtian, and <hi>God ſave him</hi> from eternal evils, which are evil to him as a man, a King, a Chriſtian: Even thus</p>
            <closer>God ſave the King, And let all Loyall loving Subjects ſay AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:168890:23"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle, p. 1. l. 8. for <hi>a,</hi> r. <hi>ſo:</hi> p. 2. l. 16. r. <hi>Pathos,</hi> p. 3. l. 9. r. moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded l. for ſcantly r. more ſecurely; Contents, p. 1. l. 19. r. caſe; p. 2. l. 6. r. compaſſion: l. 9. for virtues, r. reaſons. Page 6. d. So; p. 10. l. 18. for at, r. out, p. 18. l. 26. for ſatisfie, r. falſify, p. 22. l. 17. for prayers, r. pains. l. 18. for now, r. nor. p. 27. l. 8. r. Chriſtians, p. 28. l. 23. for firſt, r. that is: p. 30. note, his Majeſtyes words, end l. 28. none of his. l. 29. for continue, r. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventive: Ibid. note that the 4 laſt lines, from his Majeſty to ſober Subjects, incluſively, ſhould have been in the Margin: l. <hi>ult</hi> after Subjects, add, doth abundantly verifie theſe words: p. 33. l. 20. for Tare, r. Blaze; p. 34. l. 16. after made, add more.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
